hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights as always I'm
your host Daris p uh py Wayne can't even
say my own name anymore and today I'm
joined by Dr Sam sanjie namjoshi sanjie
is an expert in data science computer
vision machine learning and
bioinformatics with strong teaching
experience in bioinformatics
Biochemistry and computational
Neuroscience he is also what I would say
is a World expert in Act of inference uh
in fact he's currently putting together
a textbook which explains the
fundamentals of the theory which will
act as a wonderful addition to the
education resources we as a community
already have sorry for butchering that
intro but sanjie welcome to the show uh
we've got past my we've got past my
least favorite part of the show which is
the introduction so we're here thank you
again for for joining me yeah thank you
so much for inviting me really
appreciate it no no it's it's it's
really is a pleasure because I have been
you know it's the least I can do I've
been benefiting a lot from your
textbook um which is not out so people
if they're if they're sort of scrambling
on on the internet to try and find your
textbook they may only find the parpet
Zulo and friston one um so you may want
to start just by saying sort of well I
think today's episode is going to be
slightly different um normally we sort
of do some deep dives into people's
papers but I think today we're going to
start at least by talking about the kind
of education side of Act of inference um
so nothing too technical necessarily but
just s of thinking about how these ideas
are permeating academic culture
intellectual culture and then sort of
broader culture but maybe where we could
start I sort of gave a very brief
introduction there is with you just kind
of outlining how you found active
inference uh because people might not be
aware of your
work sure yeah so the my path to active
inference um was really unusual I think
what was really unique about it was I
had being at a point in my career where
I was starting to figure out where all
my interests were but I didn't know that
active inference actually existed so
that was the journey toward that was
that moment of finding out that all of
my research interests were colliding in
one place and if we go back really far
to just the beginning um when I was
doing my undergraduate research I was
working in neurobiology I also worked in
genetics um I did a lot of work in
Biochemistry and a lot of my my PhD work
was actually molecular Neuroscience but
I had wanted to move into more technical
Direction so I did do uh my informatics
work in my PhD uh which introduced me
more to some of the techniques and
skills that I would need um in
computational Neuroscience which is when
my postto first post was in in that
area and it was at the end of my postto
when I was getting close to leaving
Academia that I discovered active
inference while just browsing papers
writing a grant um I was the work I was
doing was uh modeling human behavior
with reinforcement learning so there was
definitely an overlap in relationship
ship active inference but um my adviser
has said yeah yeah we we know little
about active inference we don't really
use it in the lab but um it's something
we're interested in and so that kind of
just led me in that direction and
reading some of Carl's original papers
uh that just got me off on that path and
I became really excited about learning
more about it and that's kind of where I
stumbled into the original problems of
there's just no resources out there this
was around
2018 yeah 2018 there were definitely no
resources out there uh we're doing a bit
better now we have the Institute we have
the textbook by par psul and Frist which
people can buy and then hopefully your
one which is coming out um so want to go
back it's it's interesting you said sort
of the skills that you learned in doing
bioinformatics were you know really
contributed to your capacity to sort of
pick up active inference quite
intuitively what skills are they and
what sort do you feel has benefited you
most yeah so the the skills that I'm
kind of talking about here um are very
Broad in general so when you the
strategy that I've taken with with the
textbook is really to break it down into
the language that everyone would
understand if they're in any technical
field like um you know engineering or
computer science or statistics and that
language is probability Theory you if
you strip away the neuroscience and a
lot of the other themes and ideas in
there you're left with just a mechanism
of basian inference um and a lot of uh
the bionformatics methodology that I was
using in my PhD when you look at it they
boil down to some probabilistic
formation so I had some of that
background I had enough of the
background in the neurosciences and
enough in the probabilistic reasoning
side to be able to translate that into
the active inference domain there's all
these other layers on top of it of
course but at the core that's kind of
what I see as the Baseline and that's
common to all types of statistical
modeling methods can motivate it in a
probabilistic
formulation sure and when people hear
the word probabilistic maybe they their
mind does jump to Baye but maybe it
doesn't um so active inference obviously
leans very heavily on basian inference
variational basian
inference you know to your eyes would
that be the only path that it needed to
pursue could there be any other
mathematical formulations that might
flesh out the claims of active inference
and self-organization that isn't
necessarily basian
I definitely think there there could be
multiple ways we can frame the active
inference problem um because we're you
know ultimately computational
neuroscientists or modelers they're
trying to find the most convenient way
to model a system um not just for the
purpose of making predictions but also
something that's intuitive and easy to
communicate and that makes sense to
people um when we try to formulate these
more broader claims and bigger
hypotheses about the brain um I think
it's just the convenience of the beian
formulation that things neatly fit into
this picture um but there are of course
instances where sometimes you have to
kind of force it into the picture
sometimes that's you know if we try to
modeling something um there may be other
ways to do it and um the you know their
probabilistic reasoning I think is just
a really convenient way to being able to
model dependencies among variables and
when you pair that with this Dynamic
formulation you talk about dynamical
systems in a probabilistic setting um
all the tools that you get out of it I
think are really important for being
able to model the brain but it's
probably not the only way we could we
could conceive of yeah I feel like I
mean again I'm coming into this very new
because you know I've discovered this
during my masters which was you know a
year ago so I'm pre-doc I'm I'm very
sort of babyish into this field but when
you read the kind of history of I guess
computational Neuroscience or
computational psychology it feels like
there was this transition between
dynamical system into active inference
so we haven't really touched actually on
dynamical systems theory on this podcast
in in part because it's an active
inference podcast but in part because
it's it's Technical and I don't really
have the sort of chops to get into that
but I've been reading a little bit of
Scott kelo's work and getting into sort
of meta stability maybe you could just
very briefly it doesn't need to be super
deep but talk about how we get you know
what does that transition path look like
from dynamical systems what the in what
are the key insights from dynamical
systems because Carl was working in you
know in dynamical systems in the late
90s and the early 2000s and what does
that add or what does that what the
convergence points between that and an
active
inference so the biggest uh thing about
it is that when you when you look at the
history of um active inference and you
go back to the 90s a lot of the work
that uh was inter interacting
intersecting with Carl's work was the
work that was going on at the Gatsby
computation unit at UCL um and so a lot
of the uh what you would call the uh
figures the grand figures in
unsupervised learning techniques and
beijan networks we're being developed uh
people like Hinton harani and um David
McKai and there are many others as well
we're developing those techniques in the
1990s um and because of uh you know
frisen working at UCL as well there was
a lot of overlap in in knowledge of
course he was attending a lot of the
same meetings and conferences and things
like that and adapted that into SPM um
if I'm not mistaken I think SPM 2 which
was uh the 2002 version I believe
switched into the beijan world from the
more frequentist version of SPM in
earlier editions and so you have this
unsupervised learning idea which I think
is really deeply powerful because um a
classic problem in in Dynamic systems is
you know the idea of filtering you have
um some observed data that links to some
unobserved process and you have to
figure out what can we learn about about
this process that generated that data
from just these noisy samples alone and
there is a really great paper um garmani
and I think I might be pronouncing this
wrong but rois it's R Weis I believe um
I think it's 1999 paper they reformulate
all the unsupervised learning problems
and these ideas of um the expectation
maximization algorithm variational Bays
they kind of put it all together and
show you how you can model State space
equations in a Invasion setting and I
think that's kind of the start of this
move in that direction um and there's a
great thesis be 2003 um uh PhD thesis
which then kind of puts all those ideas
together and I think uh the basic way of
looking at it is that you're doing beian
inference but you can look at it as
beian inference over time and with all
of the work in the 90s with Dynamic
models of the brain like you you
mentioned Kelo and there others as well
um looking at the brain is a dynamic
system which uh changes in a way that
settles toward some kind of
equilibrium um those ideas I think when
you combine with the basion inference
and all of these unsupervised learning
ideas coming together under Dynamic
systems umbrella uh it's a natural fit
to then say okay how can we model the
brain with certain equations uh where
these unknown states trying to be
estimated and the equilibrium solution
is the most likely estimate of those
States given the
data cool yeah I want to get into
expectations maximization cuz I was just
very excited when I feel like I learned
what it was although I'm probably
missing something but I thought it was
incredible um but just to sort of finish
up on the dynamical systems theory and
and the sort of
chronology I guess there's two questions
one is a very broad question which is in
some ways is active inference a kind of
apotheosis or the end point of dynamical
systems fa can it be couched within that
overarching frame and then second point
which is a little bit more specific is
in terms of meta stability so this idea
that the let's say the neuronal Dynamics
are jumping from as you say like an
attracting set or what people talk about
Wells but it never really settles in one
place that will sound very similar you
know very familiar to people who are
familiar of active inference uh so I
guess is my question is what's
interesting there I guess is the kind of
as you say over ESS the DI chronicity of
meta stability where does it diverge
from active inference what is it kind of
convergence point and then again yeah
how does that contribute to the
difference between dynamical systems
theory and active
inference yeah so that's of course there
a huge I think so much could be written
and talked about on this so I'll kind of
give like the sure the high level answer
my interpretation of that which is that
um active inference I think is what's
really interesting about it um if you
look at the equations um of active
inference this paper is um it's
hierarchical models in the brain
Carl's 2008 I want to say paper um and
it's a great paper because he spends a
lot of time digging back through that
old literature from the 1990s and then
saying look if we add all these other
extra elements onto it which is what
some of the um those papers were doing
for in your Imaging setting um we get
all of these different techniques that
fall out of it so it's kind of like uh
active in even if you just take out the
active part just the perception alone
perception of both hidden States uh
learning model parameters and also
learning the Precision of uh sensory
data or your priors all of that
information um in one algorithm if you
start taking all these special cases you
can get all the neural network and
supervised learning literature you can
get um all these unsupervised learning
problems filtering problems uh whether
it's dynamic or static so I I see that
as kind of like active inference um is
sort of a global overarching method uh
you could you could apply to any kind of
um stochastic time series type of
analysis um if you take out the action
part then you just have purely a
perception part looking for patterns in
data but if you had action in there then
you kind of recover this idea of control
systems and the ability to control um
stochastic dynamical systems um in a
particular setting so that's the way I
view it is kind of like you get all
these other things that kind of fall out
of it um so as far as I I can see it is
it's kind of the broadest generalization
one could imagine of these kinds of
basan motivated statistical systems sure
I'm curious again before we get into the
sort of nitty-gritty I mean I'm I'm not
here to sell active inference but I'm
always curious you know about it scope
about what the next 10 years is going to
the next 20 years as you say in the 90s
I I had Chris fron and he was sort of
telling me just how exciting it was in
the 90s uh because you had the Gatsby
you had all the psychological work the
kind of pure psychological work that he
was doing and then the kind of Middle
Ground that Carl was occupying which was
a sort of foot in both U you know
lands and as you say they kind of
coalesced in the late 2000s and in the
2010s I'm wondering whether you can see
any other sort of not a rival Theory but
something that could you know if we're
talking about dialectics and we end up
with some symphysis what are the kind of
dialectical uh you know counterparts to
act of inference in the 2020s and the
2030s is there anything that it's going
to synthesize with to give us something
even bigger and broader and more
overarching or is this you know I'm I
don't know why I've gone very hegelian
but is this the kind of is this the kind
of end of history in some
ways uh yeah that's that's a really good
question and I I think it's you know
it's really hard to to know I think at
the moment right now if you think about
just um if you're talking in purly
computational terms um you know everyone
is talking about deep learning um and
that's what of course is an industry all
over what you know research programs are
focusing so much on deep learning
systems and that's kind of the same
thing you know could is claims have been
made about that as well right the Deep
learning is the end game and so
everything will fall you know it'll kind
of become the the main
methodology um I mean there other there
are not like a lot of other things that
I think have the same broad scope trying
to Encompass so many different areas I
think that's kind of the the biggest
advantage of active inference is the
unification um but there's something to
be said about the fact that you know
active inference uses one objective
function to do everything um you know
how far can we get with that you know is
it better to have tailor made systems
where for different problems you have
really specific types of objective
functions um you know there to me I
would say like the biggest Contender or
biggest rival to active inference isn't
one specific field but more an approach
of just saying um how can we engineer
problems in a really specific
way um with very heavily tailored
objective functions that satisfy a
particular problem domain or something
like that because I'm wondering if you
run into a problem with this sort of
generalist specialist issue where active
inference is kind of great at everything
but maybe not uh maybe can be
outperformed by a specialist system
that's really tailor designed for that
kind of data right I think that's
exactly right I mean the university that
I work at for my day job which is not
Super Active inferenced inferencing a
Royal Holloway there's a lot of RL
modelers
um and when I speak to them that is the
kind of I mean they're very obviously
very respectful and very interested in
active inference modeling but I think
that is in many ways the critique which
is
that sure the free energy principle
might be applicable to everything but as
you say in the very sort of particular
domain you've got to do the model
comparison and if you're RL like if if
your RL uh model works better than so be
it I think the act of inference was
response to that would always be well
you can just Encompass RL with active
inference so whatever claims you're
making about RL will be
ultimately you know will ultimately be
yeah you know taken up by active
inference I guess the one difference and
you you have to tell me about this
because you know you're saying you're
starting in RL and then found active
inference is that active inference is
very strong on the as if as if theology
as if it's doing variational basian
inference is RL does RL have an
equivalent so does RL say um that you
know individuals look as if they're
maximizing a reward function or is there
a kind of more ontological claim that no
they actually are doing that and you can
see that in neurons and then maybe in
that case you know just in terms of the
philosophical uh strength of these
positions if RL is making more solid
ontological claims then maybe your RL
researchers are going to get excited
over
that so there's two different angles
that I would kind of up take this
question from and it's you know when we
talk about active inference or
reinforcement learning are we talking
about it from the perspective of what
can we do in build of these systems or
are we talking about you know the as if
nature as in like we're trying to model
specifically the brain and we want to go
for biological plausibility because you
know ultimately if we're just trying to
build you know an AI like you know when
I say AI I mean uh an intelligence that
mimics animal and human behavior maybe
we don't need to model it perfectly
after the brain we can get the as if the
as if part can get us you know it may
not be exactly the same as right as
biological intelligence yeah but it's
it's a version of intelligence that does
the same things and as far as anyone
looking from the outside it effectively
functions in the same way so that's kind
of like that's sort of like I think with
with both reinforcement learning and
active inference um you kind of see the
split like reinforcement learning
started as you know looking at models of
human behavior and um and human animal
behavior and then got taken off by into
the into the computer science realm
where it then all these new techniques
that have been developed after it may
not necessarily resemble the brain
anymore so it's when we talk about RL
it's it's hard to you know what what
does that mean because it's so many
different things now and the same thing
is kind of happening with active
inference right where we started in that
realm and now we're in a place where
we're applying it to robots and other
things and ways that may not be
necessarily biologically
plausible um so I guess the direct
answer to your question is
um I think it I think we need to Define
what RL and active inference means
specifically to be able to to kind of
characterize the asness of it um and I
think the other issue is that it's
really hard to test these kinds of
things like how do you test that neurons
are representing things in a certain way
you're always kind of locked into some
kind of philosophical um backbone
whenever you do these experiments too um
you know and so I to some degree I feel
like as if is maybe the best you can do
and it's all about predictability like
are we predicting the activity of
neurons and what they're doing and
that's kind of the best thing you can
get to I think that the on ontological
part of it that's hard to close that Gap
and I don't know if we'll get there at
least in the in you know the next decade
or so maybe a lot longer to get to that
point yeah I think as a naive psychology
slash philosophy student I sort of came
in and thought well we'll just get to
the construct
but you realize that in well in
Psychology especially you know if I'm
studying if I've got an attention
Paradigm I just take for granted that I
know what attention is but like frankly
there's well was this good paper
actually I think it was homel uh the
title of it was no one knows what
attention is and I kind of think you can
have that for every construct I mean
there anyone really and and in some ways
that's a shame but as you say it's
predictability I think the difference
where well my stance is that I'm not an
out andout modler so my interest is in
saying okay well let's take a cognitive
function like attention how close can we
get to well let's just say this a
general agreement we have over what
attention is and fundamentally that's a
phenomenological thing because we only
really know what attention is by paying
attention to our own attention in some
strange way and I guess this brings me
to ask do you think in some ways like
you know you saying we got active
inference in robotics and you got
someone like me who's trying to do
phenomen ology and active inference then
you've got people applying it to atoms
and you know the the very fundamental
physics and so on do you think active
inference is risking becoming too
diffuse that it's just this kind of on
size fits all and let's just take any
phenomenon phenomenon and see what we
can say about it in terms of variational
basing inference and if
so is that a kind of big problem what's
the kind of narrowing down or
refinement of the theory and the
community that that might need to
happen so this is this speaks to a
problem that I've already run into when
I'm uh people are reading drafts of my
chapters I'm already seeing that
everyone kind of has their own vision
and understanding of what active
inference is there's sort of this local
knowledge problem right everyone comes
in it from a different angle and the way
that they've interacted with it means
that they see it uh they see active
inference in in one light or another um
and that is a big challenge because
there is this prediction ER of people
reading the book they're like well I
never thought of active inference that
way here's what it means to me they're
expecting it to be a certain way um and
I think this becomes especially true the
further out you go from the actual
mathematics yeah because the actual
mathematical models they of course
there's always interpretation of what
what the math means but they're a lot
easier to say like hey I made the
simulation here's what it's doing uh you
know okay it converge it didn't converge
we have these tools and metrics and
things that we can say what's happening
when we we run a model but when you
start getting to the outer edges of that
where there's a lot of the like the
philosophy you know there's active
inference in and ecosystems and weather
and active inference um you know talking
about like plants and how plants can be
predicting um and we start I mean that's
kind of the the real the draw for beian
mechanics is that it's well it should
apply to any dynamical system that are
trying to predict one another within
certain set of constraints which should
cover a very broad spectrum of types of
systems um I definitely think that's
both hurt and helped active inference I
think there's a
tendency um in any field when you know
the classic um when all you have is a
hammer everything looks like a nail um
if your proposal is vague enough you can
probably massage it into the active
inference framework but then when you
start going down further and further the
actual math of it okay so what is what
is the math of ecosystems and
communities and economics like huge all
these agents that are all their own
generative models all interacting in a
big you know group what does that look
like mathematically does it really scale
to that level um or is there some other
generalization we're missing um I I
think it's great to speculate personally
as someone I just love the idea of
taking into these new areas I think
that's what Spurs creativity and allows
people to then explore new ideas but I
think we should distinguish carefully
between active inference itself and
applications of active inference in a
theoretical sense philosophical
applications of
it yeah yeah yeah yeah I mean this has
been my personal experience which
actually is that my life becomes a lot
easier when I'm writing papers to stick
to the maths as in not that I'm writing
mathematical papers but that when I have
the very just very simply if I have the
variational free energy formula and the
expected free energy formula in front of
me I actually can't go too wrong in some
ways um not that I run the derivations
and obviously there is an appeal to
Authority that those derivations hold
but you know I remember my introduction
you know when I started thinking about
active inference and reading the kind of
seminal philosop philosophical Pieces by
Andy Clark and Jacob Hobby and these are
you know Classics and very
important but you then go well am I
learning about predictive coding okay
what are the hell all of these equations
doing the variational mess and then
that's really a mess for a lot of people
and so I think for a lot I don't know my
experience has been when people ask me
okay what what is act of inference I
literally just go well if you have just
the variational free energy formula like
let's just start there um a question
that comes to mind actually when it
comes to sort of talking to people about
active inference is that people will say
okay well what every Theory's got its
Miracles every theory is got it axioms
what are the axioms of Act of inference
what is it presuppositions and I say
well I kind of think there are two but I
think you'll be able to tell me there
are more one I say you have to kind of
accept that there's thingness that there
are individuated things and I think
that's an actually really interesting
development that could go which is like
what is an individuated thing like how
do we even get there how do we start
there but that's a kind of axum and then
the other one I think is time that you
have that you have this kind of movement
back to the attracting set over
time is there anything more that we
should add to that kind kind of set of
presuppositions to active influence rest
on I know there's going to be stuff like
ergodicity which is a little bit more
technical but there anything more that I
should be telling people about when they
ask me a question like
that so I think the the biggest
motivating motivating factors here uh
what you said I think is those are
definitely um really important
assumptions and I think there are others
that can be paired with it or um maybe
are broader categories and one is that
when you talk about thingness and
existence right like we're defining what
existence means like existence is is a
philosophical concept that has been
explored for you know thousands of years
so there's many different ways of
looking at existence I think this is
more of a pragmatically motivated way of
saying that you know when we when
something exists it exists meaning that
we can measure its properties over an
appreciable amount of time so thingness
of course there is that problem like how
do you define thingness how do you
define what how one or two things are
identical to one another um you know
there're all these kind of philosophical
questions and you get into like mology
about how parts and holes come together
and what is a part and you know there
there's all kinds of topics one could go
into here um sure that have you know
Rich literature right but um that's one
part of it is that we have to talk about
what is it we're actually talking about
I think that's one assumption that you
that you uh mentioned and along with the
time assumption it's the idea that we're
taking a physics perspective which
physics has a very has a particular
reductionist way of looking at the world
and here we're saying that you know
everything we're modeling can come down
to stochastic differential equations um
because everything in active inference
ultimately is a form formulation of a
stochastic differential equation where
you have two different systems that are
themselves modeled that way and you look
at their
interaction so I mean there are some
other things too like you know you talk
about like sparse coupling in Markov
blankets there's there's other like
little bits bits and pieces that are in
here um that are more the philosophical
foundations but then when you go into
the mathematics there are a lot of
little simplifying assumptions here and
there that you could toss in um one
example is like the llas approximation
which is used in active inference it
makes it simpler um there is some
biological reasons to believe that that
that assumption is true same with the
mean field approximation there are
reasons to believe that the brain has
these sort of independent separations um
but it becomes especially true when
you're getting to the actual mathematics
they're all these little pieces gaussian
assumptions for example um that you
start to add on there yeah excellent
okay so yeah let's Okay so yeah so the
one thing that I've been thinking about
is what AC should I tell people then the
other thing that people ask me is well
what is it in the first place and your
explanation at least in the first
chapter I think of the textbook which is
the kind of um this notion that the
brain is sort of Trapped In This Cranium
and has no access to the world and
receives it through this uh you know
these sensory data channels was
incredibly I mean one hears about these
in you know these examples in philosophy
but I think that was really on the money
so maybe you could do a better job than
me just saying well what is the fun like
if we're just talking about human well
cognitive creatures creatures that are
trying to exert some control some active
sensing movement well or even perception
you know within its environment and
trying to survive let's say without
invoking any strong tileology what is
the problem that they
face yeah yeah the biggest problem is
you know absolutely that the physical
systems that make up the world um are
hugely complex so they by complex I mean
there are many many variables that
change um you know obviously there
there's a lot of structure in the world
that we can leverage but moment to
moment um things can move and be very
volatile um and so that's I think this
is getting a bit into other topics but
that's the reason why we formulate um
you know things like culture and society
and structure into our world we make the
world more predictable by by having
these elements in there that just make
there's less overhead computational
overhead and I think that's why you know
groups of uh we look at the evolutionary
history of humans um social groups uh
small social groups and um the ability
to see others as part of your whole like
you're you're part of other you're part
of a community of people where you all
collectively care about each other I
think these are all survival techniques
that come into play um and a necessity
for making the world more certain
because things can change at any moment
you know even just you know you drive to
work one day um and the road's closed
right like their decisions even in a
regular World there are always things
that come up all the time in your
personal lives you get sick um you know
things come up meetings get canceled and
you're you have to go you know change
your schedules things like that these
are all part of our everyday lives and
ultimately I think the idea is that when
we think about active inference it's the
idea of if we're trying to deal as these
biologically from the biological
perspective we're looking at humans
trying to make sense of their world and
quickly identify what's going on and
quickly make a decision for the purpose
of survival which is the whole point
it's not to represent the world
perfectly and all these other things we
might want to do it's literally to be
able to survive and pass on our genes to
the Next Generation then what are the
minimum requirements to be efficient to
do that and also make those decisions in
a really quick time knowing that the
computational complexity of the world is
enormous and we're dealing with like you
know fractal levels of systems of nested
uh hierarchies of things that are
changing dynamically how can we leverage
the data that we have to quickly make
decisions and I think if we're talking
the most broad way spectrum of thinking
about active inference it's the looking
at how the brain has solved this problem
and attempting to write that down
mathematically or at least something
that behaves like how the brain how we
perceive the brain to be behaving cool
yeah so the way that I kind of see it
it's very core is that you have as you
say a coupled system the envir the agent
in the arena the environment and the
organism and the organism hasn't got
direct access to the environment but it
has direct access to sensory
observations and so it develops a So-Cal
generative model which is trying to in
some ways mimic or replicate the
so-called generative process generative
process is the fact that there are
so-called hidden causes or latent causes
out there in the world which actually
generate those sensory data and we're
trying to have a model of of model of
the world or be a model of the world
whatever you want uh which maps on to
that allbe it not perfectly and I think
this is a really important point because
well then we would just be the world and
we don't want to be the world we want to
be us and so we have our preferences and
whatnot now let's I I'm I want to go to
sort of expect
maximization because I think it's a
really interesting way into this problem
so if we were let's let's not even think
about genetic priors or phenotypic
priors because in some ways that hacks
its way to an answer if I was John
locken I thought the brain was really a
tabularasa like I literally give it
nothing but the capacity to take in
sensory
observations what's my way of building a
generative model I have my my sensory
observations
and that's about it and I want to build
some hidden I want to build a model with
hidden causes and parameters that relate
the hidden causes to those sensory
observations what's my what what is the
kind of technical way of doing
that so you know so if we're talking in
kind of like you said like a tabularasa
kind of thing where it's I's thought
that you can think of like maybe like a
uniform prior was the way that Invasion
inference You' think about like you
don't necessarily have any particular
belief about what the state of the world
is like uh you know denovo and you would
accumulate over time um so I think like
that this is when when we do active
inference simulations we're essentially
mimicking that because you can you know
you might have like some uh you know
very basic simulations you can you can
put a uniform
distribution over your model and you're
kind of just saying all states are kind
of flat there's no I don't have any one
belief that one state is more likely
than any other uh in my environment and
I have to just learn what is out there
um with just this really simple model um
I think it's really hard to not have
some assumptions because even in a model
like that you still have a gaussian
assumption about likelihood and prior um
and you also have some kind of
generating equation where you have some
mapping that's there about okay how do
what is the relationship between
environment States and the sensations
that I as this agent experience those
are kind of built into the model so I
think there's always I think it'd be
very hard to start from nothing um other
than doing kind of like a um sort of
like an evolutionary kind of algorithm
where you just have random connections
forming over time and the ones that
survive are the ones that make good
connections and that's probably how you
get off the ground in the first place is
like in a limited environment there's
just random selection going on and you
just have you could have just a big set
of random Connections in in a likelihood
um and even maybe just choose from a
random set of families of distributions
from the exponential family and then
just kind of see run it and see what you
get out of that which ones survive and
the one that survives you propagate it
to the next generation and you continue
to run more experiments in a dynamic
environment and see which one comes out
of that and what you'll probably be left
with at a certain point is something
like those kind of priors we talked
about like where you were saying not to
get too much into like the genetic
priors and stuff like that they probably
come from that kind of a process is that
you have supervised learning that's kind
of what evolution is it's like many many
years of this sort of training with the
environment and the ones that succeed
are the ones that pass to the Next
Generation yeah so I think this is a
really interesting question actually
because I've never really thought about
it
but I don't want to get too
philosophical because it's it's an
unanswerable question but as you say if
there was no so we might have some prior
we can have like a gussian assumption
but let's say we just actually had no
prior expectations over latent causes
mhm it seems to me that the the the
space of potential latent causes is near
infinite at least in its gradations
right I mean I could go from you know
every single decimal point all the way
down which makes me think that at the
very Inception of life let's say how do
we even get off the ground at all given
like that every single potential hidden
causes as likely as another and once I
have one or two then sure I can
bootstrap off those and and get to some
uh descriptive viability in terms of my
model but if we were if you literally
had something that had like none Z maybe
some assumptions like a gan assumption
but in terms of actually like expected
States
none how do you even get off the ground
on r on Randomness because can't you
just go in infinite
directions so um are you familiar uh
with Terence Deacon's uh Terence Deens a
philosopher he has something called the
autogen and his 2011 book I'm faintly
familiar with him but not enough to
really say much about him okay so I I'm
going to appeal to this because I think
it's a really interesting way of kind of
motivating this question and this is
getting to more in the broader topics
about like autop is self-organizing and
self-maintaining systems um I would say
that his example of the autogen um is is
an example of um and I'll explain this
in a second of of what you know how
could something get off the ground from
basically nothing and so when he
proposes the autogen um the very brief
idea is that he says suppose you just
have some molecules that are just in a
liquid some kind of
um solvent and they're just these
molecules floating around um and when
they're in close enough proximity to
each other uh they're able to form a
little catalytic reaction so imagine
four molecules one makes the other in a
chain um such that a makes b b makes c c
makes D but D makes a so now you have
this little self-sustaining propagating
chain just because of pure chemical
Dynamics um but if there's not enough
raw materials to make those those
proteins it'll eventually fall apart
yeah but suppose that a an enclosed
membrane depends on some of those
proteins so then you get this positive
feedback loop where um the existence of
those proteins encloses it in a small
space and so it perpetuates that
reaction and also the raw materials are
outside of that membrane so that
whenever the membrane deteriorates
because there's lack of components the
raw materials just float back in and
they res sustain the system again which
then rebuilds that cell wall or you can
think of it as just it could be just
molecular components that are just
housing that reaction in a small space
so in that small space you effectively
limited the space bace to very small
number of things and the breakdown of
that system is a negative that negative
feedback cycle ends up causing the
system to then re again right so you
could motivate that probabilistically
like um you can make a simulation where
that you know those are all in
probability distributions and we're not
assigning agency to that it's not like
it knows what it's doing but one can see
how you could scale that up into more
and more complex systems and
arguably that's exactly what's happening
in the brain if you think about it in
terms of self-organization you're just
looking at another set of positive
negative feedback loops on a huge scale
that we describe in the language of
probability Theory um so that's another
way in I think it well it's very
obviously it's very reminiscent of Auto
Prius as first introduced by verel and
Matana and then sort of taken up in the
90s by people like Evan Thompson but I
don't I I'm sort of stretching into my
past reading here and I'm not 100% sure
that something like a classic autopoetic
system needs to break down its uh you
know needs a breakdown of its membrane
in order to build up its membrane I
think you can invoke something like a
partially permeable membrane where you
just have like the constant flooding of
U raw materials which allow you know
allow the metabolism to happen that
still like recreates that because
obviously the partial peral membrane
itself is going
to you know it's going to dissolve or
break down because of entropy and so you
you allow it to build back up but it's
it's more or less the same I guess to be
a philosopher an annoying philosopher
you continue to ask well how do we get
the kind of what would be operating
organizational closure whereby uh you
have a you know a instigating B which
instigates C which instigates D but then
that also instigates a like how does
that Loop get off the ground in the
first place because I feel like autop
pesis is a very good description of
things as they are and the classic
example is the cell you know the cell
which creates itself from within but I
guess the question is you know how does
that circularity how does that circular
causality as they say get going in the
first place and and I think that's
probably at this moment in time an an
unanswerable question I definitely agree
so first of all just to say that like
yeah this is not the only kind of you
know system we could imagine this is
just one example that I think just
captures the basic ideas and there may
be many other ways of doing this um this
is getting a little bit out of my this
is definitely out of my field of
expertise but just from uh when I was in
in graduate school there were Labs um
friends of mine that worked in labs in
synthetic biology um and they were
building that you were using DNA and
other types of other molecules like
proteins and they were doing experiments
exactly like these where um
autocatalytic reactions would just form
uh given certain set of conditions being
met um and so they would just you know
put particular compounds in because you
don't always know which ones will work
but you can toss them in and under
specific conditions of heat and pressure
and whatever uh salts and whatever
compounds are needed um Metals you end
up getting autocatalytic Loops forming
very simple ones that of course break
down over time um I don't think anything
like the autogen as far as I I know has
been replicated in a lab um but at least
like the getting off the ground part I
think just from um you're probably
familiar with Stuart Kaufman's term like
order for free um you you do have uh
like especially when your state space is
constrained when there's only a certain
set of possibilities you have less
possibilities and then you kind of get
this idea where where one system starts
forming you constrain the state space
further and you get this kind of
building Domino reaction where
eventually you end up getting something
that seems convergent because of small
little chains of random decisions that
were kind of made along the way um so
that's kind of one way I look at it I I
don't know too much about synthetic
biology so that's not my my area but
yeah well I had Mike levanon and I
should have asked him uh my um so let's
then build in something like so
evolutionist bestowed on us these
genetic priors um which I don't think we
need to necessarily get into what is the
essence of them um because the nativist
position or what really is a kind of
Prior or uh prior knowledge is still
quite fuzzy I feel like whether it's a
mechanism or an actual piece of
knowledge and this goes all the way back
to Chomsky but what's the kind of so I
want to I I want to get to expect
expectation
maximization um whether that's deriving
a prior from parameters and an observ
ation or whether that's deriving par um
parameters from a prior observation
what's this kind of it's just very
there's a very beautiful again it's kind
of like a circular causality whereby you
can derive one from and it's a kind of
work in progress Tri and eror process
but you'll be far better at explaining
it to me so for the audience who don't
know what expectation maximization is
what is it and what does it give us what
how can we bootstrap our way to
intelligence with
it so expectation maximization uh is
algorithm that was it was developed in
uh 1978 paper I think it's Dempster is
the paper the author first author on
that paper um and what was essentially
happened in the 90s was uh that
algorithm was kind of put into the
unsupervised learning uh foundations
that were going on in that time uh
specifically what's called linear
gaussian systems that's where um it was
being uh understood in that particular
context um and you can see that
variational inference is kind of like a
more broader perspective on expectation
maximization so from the perspective
you're asking about the EM expectation
maximization algorithm um is a way of
essentially there's kind of a bootstrap
going on here where so on the one hand
you have some kind of a model and I'm
I'm speaking more from the the uh
predictive coding type of perspective on
or unsupervised learning perspective I
should say is a bit more accurate On Em
there's many different ways you can
interpret it so this is this is
particular way of looking at it um in
the in the systems where you have latent
variables so you have something unknown
and all you have is sensory data of some
kind um and so the idea is well the
problem is that you're trying to figure
this out that what you're trying to do
is you're saying okay we know that there
are some states out there in the world
and they're generating data and there's
some function that relates that has
parameters that relates the that
relationship so for example in a linear
setting um the relationship between
hidden States and sensory data will just
form a a line just a linear relationship
maybe it's just uh you know just as an
example it could just be 3x plus one so
you take any hidden State value multiply
by three you add one and that's what
your data is well there are there could
be parameters that we might add in there
so other little other things that could
change the nature of that
relationship the problem is you don't
know that so you don't know what those
parameters actually are but you also
don't know the hidden state so you
basically have two things that you're
missing uh parameters in this sense are
not random variables they're treated in
the EM algorithm they're just uh Point
estimates they're single values um but
then you have this probabilistic system
on the other side here generating that
information your hidden states have
noise on them so now you have the
situation all you have here is just some
data so can you take that data and from
that data learn about the other parts of
the system that you don't know and the
reason this works is because the data is
conditioned on those things it's
affected by it it's not like in
isolation in some sense you can think of
it like they they lie behind the data
itself and they're part of that process
in some way the problem is it's all
mixed together so this is sometimes
motivated in like a signal um blind
Source separation problem or signal
unmixing in um uh in Signal processing
literature um and so the EM algorithm is
a a very clever way of getting off the
ground so to speak um you describe it
kind of like the circular causality or
something like that it's kind of a
bootstrapping perspective where you say
well I don't know what that hidden state
is out there but I can start from a
random guess and give my expectation of
what I think it is what's the most
likely value it probably is given what I
currently
believe and then from that hidden State
you do maximum likelihood estimation to
say well here's what from if this state
is this way here's what I think the
parameter is most likely to be um given
that I've just estimated what the state
is and then you you go back to the next
round you say Okay usually you can
motivate this in terms of a like a
gradient descent or there's many ways to
to look at this problem but basically uh
usually use the log likelihood as your
as your objective function or negative
log likelihood and you say okay well I'm
going to make another adjustment down
the log likelihood um for a new guess at
what the par what the hidden states are
what my expectation is now that I have
those new parameters I just I just
estimated and then you go back another
round again and you keep going in this
circle until you hit convergence which I
will say that em natively um often has
trouble converging so you have to you
may have to add other constraints to
make that system work but ultimately you
get off the ground with just sensory
data alone you are able to estimate
other things that you don't know um
that's the essence of also variational
Bays is very similar to that as well
that was what I thought the answer to my
tabaza question was but we got to autens
which was which was cool um yeah there's
I guess yeah I guess uh you mentioned I
was going to ask um you mentioned
maximum likelihood estimation so I think
it's wor people might not know what that
means um what what is Mac maximum
likelihood estimation and how does it
feed into this
picture so maximum likelihood estimation
is a really well-known statistical
technique um that has its origin in many
different it's used in a lot of frequent
statistics as well um as Bean there are
many ways to kind of formulate it but
the basic idea that the way that I like
to think about it in terms of um this
sort of predictive coding or active
inference-based um
perspective um just because that's kind
of the Lang common language we're using
right now um is to say um we have some
um unknown variable of some kind so that
you have uh something that's latent in
this case um can we estimate the most
likely value of um that particular
unknown variable instead of the whole
distribution so you could get back the
whole distribution and do basian
inference or you could turn it more into
this restricted problem where you get an
estimator which tells you the mode or
mean of that distribution instead y um
and you need some kind of a likelihood
model to do that and you make some
assumption about okay I have P of y
given X that's your likelihood model you
have some guess about how uh
observations and states are related and
you invert that relationship by just
finding the mode only so the most likely
value instead of the whole distribution
and it can be an easier less
computationally expensive problem uh
that you can get like a simple update
equation for given what distribution
you're using um but the problem is that
there there may it may be a biased
estimator it may not be exactly right
given the other assumptions that are in
your model um so it's just a convenient
way to estimate what parameters are
that's kind of the most common way of
using it is to say I have some you can
use it in linear regression for example
what are the most likely parameters that
are give rise to this particular model
that I
haveh interesting you know it's funny
there well there a couple of things that
come to mind one is that people will be
you know people who did what you would
call High School maths what I would call
Senior School maths uh would be very
familiar with the terms right mean mode
me
whatever and yet it sounds really
complicated so I'm kind of bringing it
back to this education
point is it really complic I had I had a
question R down which I haven't asked
but you know people think that the m is
really
complicated is it really
complicated or does it seem or does it
just seem really
complicated I have to admit that um the
perspective that I'm going to give you
now might have been different than my
perspective 5 years ago so it's hard to
tell sometimes because you're so deep in
something right is it now appearing easy
because you know you've learned all the
material because I remember how I felt
when I first encountered all this stuff
so I'll say that um beian mechanics I
think that side of things is a lot
harder to explain and a lot more
technical um you can motivate everything
in there as well probably within
probability Theory I would say and
that's kind of the approach I'm going to
take um in the second book is going to
be in that
direction but if we're just restricting
to active inference um
I would personally say that it's not as
complicated as it looks um it all can be
motivated in terms of simple
distributions um gines are easy to deal
with means and modes I think what gets
complicated is when people start dealing
with linear algebra where you just have
multiple dimensions in your system then
the notation gets kind of very abstract
and compact but in the univariate case
um everything has a really strict and
very simple interpretation that you can
you can think about in terms of like
equations how you're deriving things um
personally I think it's almost there
there are times when I'm writing and I
look back at the equations and I'm like
wow there there's so few things in here
really um when you think about what
things you need to tune um and obviously
when you're building like huge you know
like you're looking for replicating all
aspects of human and animal behavior yes
it's going to get complicated but the
core actual methodology I would argue is
something you could teach to high
schoolers um you may not use all the
technical terms but you could get them
to run a simulation and see what's going
on and play around with variables and
they'll have a pretty intuitive
understanding of what's happening for
example right and so how would you
recommend so people you know people
might not have access to your textbook
or they won't and you know if they in
the public and the par petul and friston
textbook although it's very
good does I think for a lot of people
feel like they've been thrown in the
deepend that you know certain chapters I
think are are relatively
taxing what do you recommend how do you
know how do you recommend people go
about this if they're not you know if
they're like me for example you I'm
trying to pick it up and think I'm doing
okay and and learning step by step what
would you recommend people do is that
are there certain prerequisites you know
should you do a statistics course should
you do a linear algebra course should
you do a calculus course what are the
key uh fundamentals that people need to
do and and and do you have any
recommendations I mean this is also
asking for myself about how to really
what bootstrap your own learning
experience well uh of course I would I
you know that's my aim for the book is
to provide this perspective but um in
the you know in terms of prerequisites
you know when I think about um what
active inference at its real core having
a solid understanding of introductory
probability Theory so we're talking
about um something you would prob you
could learn it some people learn it in
high school um this kind of introductory
probability conditionals joint
distributions um having a good intuitive
sense of that but it would probably be
for most people it' be some
undergraduate course um the second would
be
calculus um if you want to just learn
the concepts um single variable calculus
would be enough so if you know how to
take a derivative and you know what an
integral is that's sufficient for most
things um and then the third when you
start getting into linear algebra that's
useful when you start talking about more
useful systems that are
multi-dimensional but if you're just
staying in univariate everything you can
graph you can visualize all the
equations are just numbers there's no
matrices or
vectors that core idea uh which you can
get you know the scaling of the
percentages of active inference from
zero to 100% understanding um is
definitely not linear I think it gets
you know the distance between 95 and 96
is so much bigger than like 0 to 50
right so there's levels of understanding
but I think you could get with that
alone you could get 75% of the way there
of understanding what's going on now
there isn't a lot of resources on that I
think
ultimately what you need to do is have
some very basic Python Programming
background um and being able to uh make
a very very simple simulation with the
most minimum materials this is what I
was going to ask a lot of advice that
I've got is well you know I'm going to
be doing a PhD they just say well you'll
do it during your PhD the more you do it
the more the easier it gets and I get I
actually think that's the case of a lot
of things not only I mean there are
certain things where it's not the case
actually which I think is quite
interesting so for example
philosophy I would argue that in certain
things actually sometimes your earlier
intuitions are a little bit better
because sometimes you end up down such a
rabbit hole that you are a bit blinkered
and you know I'm writing stuff like self
models well there's just so many
recursive elements to it and and so you
get a little bit stuck but I found that
for example uh coding so like R I use R
because in my daily job I do statistics
you really just learn by doing it and
then it becomes like a language in many
ways so would that be yeah I want to
hear your sort of thoughts on that
learning by doing it's not necessarily
what people have been trained to do
because we're used to going to school
and reading textbooks but it sounds
sounds like that's a really strong
recommendation on your
part yes and actually for me I love
reading textbooks that for me is how
I've always learned I've always been in
situations where I didn't have a teacher
and that's same with active inference I
didn't do research in it first I taught
myself active inference and also I
taught it while I was writing it I mean
there there isn't any resource out there
there are a lot of you know little
tricks that are in people's heads so
even when I have all the model in front
of me just tuning it with like learning
rates and stuff there's all kinds of
behavior I have no idea what's going on
just comes from trial and error um so I
think yeah I have the perspective of yes
I I love learning from textbooks but I
learned the most teaching was one way
teaching it to people but also through
just messing around with the models and
the crazy thing about the active
inference models that's really really
nice about them the simple ones is that
um if you're just trying to just do a
very basic simulation everything is
analytic update rules so if you can just
take a derivative and you can do a bit
of addition and subtraction um knowing
how all the pieces fit together is a
challenge but the actual code for a
really simple active inference model is
just a bit of for Loops addition and
subtraction and some like updating of of
some data structures just so you can
keep track of the history of how the
system evolves over time um the actual
core of it is really simple to implement
and um that's that's my experience is
the what I try to do in the book um uh
especially in the revisions I'm doing
right now going throughing doing
revisions at the moment um having pseudo
code that is nearly exact to what you
would put into python or R so you start
out you initialize these things then you
make a loop and then you update these
things in a loop and then you interact
with the environment get a new data
point or you act on it depending on what
your perception or action and you just
continue that Loop and all the equations
are right there so there may be a couple
different ways you could you know you
could put it into code But ultimately
the sequence is really clear and I think
that that part of it with a bit of
guidance um someone who doesn't have a
lot of experience in probability could
get a feel for what's going on without
even knowing all of the requisite
background um and all the details that
go into there and that's the fun part I
really want that's kind of something for
the future is to have like sliders and
stuff like on a website where you can
just play around with sliders and Learn
by just interacting with a graph that
has a pre-made model um you can get so
much intuition from just doing that
alone yeah I think that would be great I
think that would be great I also wonder
whether a thing that's been really
useful for me and and and really this is
just because of the generosity of people
who you know are being far too kind
someone like Carl yeah walking me
through a soft Max function um just
because he's nice and generous I wonder
how how much did you you know you're
saying you're teaching yourself active
inference how much did you get out of
corresponding with other people and is
there anyone that sort of comes to mind
that that sort of has you know
formalized intuitions or has been a good
sort of uh discussion
partner so possibly to my own detriment
um I seem to have a habit of having to
do everything myself um which on the one
hand is really good because I I I to
learn things really deeply and I I have
to go into it and and really understand
it but on the other it's been a big
Challenge and the honest answer to that
question is um there are very few people
that I've actually interacted with uh
personally now that I i' I've been
working at versus now since um December
and there I definitely have now started
to um for a lot of the technical
questions um um Magnus kudal is one
person who's been very very helpful on
the factor graph side lance deosta as
well uh recently we we spoke and he was
very helpful helping me out with u
generalized coordinates of motion which
are still very very tricky for me to
understand um they're pretty big
challenge in in um in active inference
models um and I would say that for me
it's been more Brute Force so there are
two or three really good reviews um
Buckley at 2017 it's very dense um also
Rafael um boax I hope I'm not
pronouncing that yeah correctly that's
another review and there are a couple
others too like the Ryan Smith's paper
with with Carl um and Christopher white
um that has the discreet time tutorial
essentially that's what I did was I took
those papers and then I scoured the
internet for code examples and little
Snippets and put all that together um
and that took me five years to get to
that point um but that's what I did is
just that and then constantly reading
papers and being confused and um so
maybe it could have been easier but
there was no active inference Institute
I didn't know people um that was the
problem I was working in isolation which
is a challenge always is yeah well good
I mean it's amazing I mean it's it's
super cool um yeah I point I I point
people in the direction of Smith and
colleagues but there are other tutorials
uh CU I've spoken to Ryan as well and
he's great and um I think that's the
easiest one although to be honest I
always I always go into it and then like
get halfway through and I'm like I've
got some philosophy to do and then
I it's a long 100 pages so really long
and I think um yeah I think you're right
you need to have the coding up with you
while you're doing it and and you're
sort of figuring things out on the go
and that's for my PhD so I'm not going
to do that yet it's an interesting point
about coding because I feel like um my
intuition here is that it's all been
happening on mat lab a very Tech this is
a very nerdy technical point but people
might find it interesting because they
might as you say go now inspired by this
and try and build their own active
inference simulations so you know Carl's
famous mat lab that you can download uh
where you know you said there I think
there is a python um there is a python
you know whatever you would call it um
package thing that you can package that
you can install thank you um what you
know is is a would you say one is
superior than the other I mean most
psychologists are used to R um what you
know what's the kind of good starting
point you mentioned python is that would
you recommend python for a starting
point so I I so the book is I'm using
python as the main language in the book
um and uh I so I I I've used R from many
as the first real language I used in in
grad school was R for most of my PhD
work so I'm familiar with r as well lab
I only have a passing familiarity with I
use it a little bit in my one of my post
STS but um like anything like any tool
you know it depends what you're trying
to do with it uh personally I think that
you can make some really quick like data
processing in R especially with like
howly becomes tidy verse and stuff like
you can do some quick like processing
and stuff you can do a lot of quick
stuff in R that's my life yeah the
tiny I love tiny vers yeah yeah it's
it's great and it's you know it made a
little language it's not even some
people might even argue it's not even R
anymore it's a new thing on top of it or
a framework but you know there's there
are ways that you can um you know you
can make a quick and dirty script in r
that does active inference super easily
you can do the same in mat lab um I find
mat lab to be really confusing
personally um and python I'm only
picking because it's kind of the de
facto language for machine learning
because um if you're trying to build big
systems with it you might get into
trouble if you don't know what you're
doing because things get very
complicated um and but if you're just
doing Simple scripts there isn't a lot
of stuff that stands in the way so I
like python because it's kind of clean
um R is fairly clean I think people I
think people are unfair to R I think it
actually is a great language um and I
would say that um there's nothing wrong
with using any of the three languages
it's just whatever you're comfortable
with um and I would say that the minimum
hello world of active inference would
probably look pretty similar in all
three languages um it really just comes
down to something like how do you you
know slicing notation and really basic
things might differ but the actual like
code there isn't anything super
specialized if you're just doing like a
really simple discret or continuous time
active inference model I'm not sure if
that answered your question yeah no no
no that my question that answer my
question and yeah I think people as you
say hope hopefully over time we'll find
more and more resources that kind of
guide them through the process we'll get
there um I want to get to versus at some
point next point but we had a good back
and forth about priors and I I feel like
it would be remiss of me not to mention
priors um I also had this chat uh with
Ronnie sladkey who had written this
paper the amigdala complex um from an
active inference perspective which I
think I mean I read a lot of active
inference papers as you can imagine not
only for this but for my own work and
that was really I think the first place
where I
really felt that the notion of Prior had
been nicely disambiguated because they
are so it's so loosely used yes so
people will talk about and I think I
think until you're familiar with
something like the pomdp scheme it's
it's very confusing because at least in
the pomdp schemes for example you have D
Matrix you know your initial State prior
you have your C Matrix the preference
prize and that begins to you know
separate things in a way that's possible
um but let's I'm you have a really nice
diagram which I wish I could show but
I'm not going to share my screen so it
won't work um but you know we have
different priors in active inference
although we make we lump them under this
kind of general term prior so we talk
about preference priors we talk about
and that kind of builds in stuff like
phenotypic priors or genetic priors and
then we also have state priors and I
think the main difference that is you
know intuitive to me and hopefully
intuitive to other people is you know in
in all aspects of life both are going to
be at play because you need to work out
where you are more or less or what's
going on and so basically what the state
you're in but then you're also always
going to have a
preferred version of that I mean it's a
terrible way to put it but you're going
to have a preferred outcome you're going
to have a preferred state that you want
to be in and there's might be a
Divergence there um is there any other
kind of type of Prior that you might
want to build into that picture and how
problematic just more generally is this
idea that we just have priors post Thea
people don't even talk about likelihood
distributions right they just talk about
prediction error or sensory data which
is confusing once you start looking at
like an a matrix so yeah let's just kind
of get into the the nitty-gritty how
many different types of priers are there
will they end up all being the same
what's the kind of situation
there I think the distinction comes down
to how we're talking about priors um
like you said right they're used in so
many different ways so I would say like
in the most General non-technical sense
when people use the word prior they
typically mean assumptions that are held
by the agent in some way some kind of
assumption and assumption can even just
mean like um you know my actions have
consequences you know I take an action I
get a sensory out you know it could even
be something like
um uh just built in assumptions about
the structure of the world itself so if
you're talking whatever right so if
you're talking very broadly yeah a
likelihood you can call it a prior if
you're saying this really really vague
sense of just anything that's your
assumption about whatever is going on
about how you think the world operates
or how your own actions operate right
now that's of course um I think where
the confusion comes from is that prior
just kind of means like presuppositions
or assumptions that are sort of just
there in the model um when I look at
when we think about prior in the beian
sense then it has to take on a really
specific meaning so I think that's where
the modeling when you talk about an
actual pom DP or you're looking at aian
Network um that to me is where you can
be a lot more um
particular about what kind of Prior
you're you're dealing with so just to be
clear here a prior in that sense means
um you have a variable whose value is
uncertain so you can have a distribution
over the values that that variable is
most most likely to take you don't know
which one is the one it's going to
actually take but you have learned from
some interaction through data um or
possibly through Evolution or through
teaching you know people learn about how
the world Works uh by parents teach us
certain priors about how using prior in
a in a bit of kind of both senses of
like um you could motivate it in an
evasion way but it' be like prior about
here is how the world works and those
could be part of your values right you
can you can think of it in such so many
broad ways so that's thing is the
problem is that we take these models
that are really simple and we're trying
to describe them attribute them to
really hugely complicated things like
culture and things like that and it's a
lot harder than what is a prior inas
Network look like when you're talking
about a culture I mean you could think
of it in 10 different ways I mean I'm
sure you could make a model for what
those priors are like and how they you
know work into a model of human behavior
for example but there is no right way to
do that I think um it depends how you're
kind of structuring the research problem
so getting more to your question you
asking like what other kind of priors
are there I mean I think there
are like like you said there are priors
about U the agent's expectations about
how the environment behaves uh it's
preferred States about what states it
would like to be in in the environment
but also um all the sort of priors that
come down for how its Body Works how
movement Works um the assumption that
you you just have about the nature of
the world and the body the nature of
your own model um that come down to
personality preferences about how you
view the world there's so many ways to
look at it so maybe a better answer
would if if we narrow the scope um
unless that answered your question not
sure no no no that that that that's
useful I mean I think something you said
that was really interesting there is
that the prior is kind of the the
the variable encoded in the prior is
random
variable um such that it's kind of the
function of other possible outcomes it's
a probability distribution but I guess
people don't think about them like that
right like intuitively you don't think
about that you go well I want to be well
let's say like a body prior I want to be
37.8 degrees celsus that's always useful
one but it's not like that right it's
it's it's over a probability
distribution
um and maybe that's worth
unpicking uh Maybe not maybe it actually
just confounds or muddies the water
somewhat but how do people how should
people sort of tackle that intuition no
I just have like so-called preferred
States and they're one thing they don't
have there's no scope for them there's
no distribution of them I just want to
be
here how do you get around that problem
building in this notion of like a
probability distribution or tending
towards a probability
distribution yeah so the answer to that
question I think comes down to Precision
so the each of the probability
distributions that we can we can you
know we talk about a prior over a
variable we're saying that that
variable I think because the
non-intuitive part is that everything is
couched in probabilistic language so one
thing that I like to kind of say is like
desire is expectation so metaphorically
when we we think about desire it's not
we want it's what you re-encode that is
what do you expect and that's a really
hard thing to do because that's not how
we think about things we don't think
about like I want to eat means I expect
to have food in my body that sounds
really weird right like it's just no
it's naturally I want to eat is just a
feeling that I have that I know that if
I have food it'll be satisfied and
that's kind of how we think about it so
when I mean Precision I mean that when
you for example you talked about body
temperature so yes I prefer my body
temperature to be at this
particular um 98 Degrees let's say
Fahrenheit um but actually the way to
say it is I expect it to be that way
because that's what your brain is
predicting and with a prior really the
truth is that there's actually a range
right because um more than likely you
can you can push that to about 104
degrees with a fever you don't want to
do that very often but you could and you
could push it the other way so now you
have a distribution that's centered on
98 Degrees now it could be very precise
when I said Precision it means how
precise are we talking is it just a
really tall point right around 98
Degrees um and for other priors it may
be more spread out like you can tolerate
a range so the priors are really useful
because then you can encode this notion
of ranges of acceptable values with a
preferred value in the middle and if
it's something where you're so certain
about it like you have this preference
this is the exact State I want to be in
nothing else then the probabilistic
notion still works you have a random
you increase the Precision till it hits
a point mass and then it becomes a
single value and you only entertain that
value for that prior so I I presume that
mathematically that that that sort of
uh that limit is basically infinite
right in in the in the actual maths and
you never actually reach it in terms of
biotic limited creatures but that aside
it's kind of that's kind of yeah I mean
in mathematically like if you look at
like Factor graphs and stuff we use
Delta functions all the time in there
and um but they're kind of yeah like
from the mathematical perspective I
think mathematicians would probably get
upset with the way they're used it's
more of a practical way of just saying
like Hey we're turning a probable
distribution into a single value so it
just becomes a number not a scaler
rather than yeah this is the So-Cal
directa Delta function that again I got
very excited over I get very excited to
though for very odd things but I guess
the philosophers would also get annoyed
about the infinity thing as well it
wouldn't just be the
mathematicians um yeah this is all
really useful for me and really
fascinating
so I guess well I guess people might
think okay so I have these probability
distributions that kind of makes sense
for me in terms of like my C Matrix my
preference priers but then how am I
going to have probability distributions
over something like a state prior um
what what I guess the question here is
what triggers that probability
distribution because it sounds like you
know sure we have uh observations and we
have a likelihood distribution and that
allows us to say okay I can do state
transitions because I have this constant
interaction of observations and States
but just from my initial
State what's the kind is is I mean I
guess the question here is is there such
a thing as an initial State um because I
think it's always a mistake to take the
generative model and slice it up in
terms of really you know discrete time
obviously you have to for modeling
purposes um but yeah I mean I'm going to
going around in circles here but my
question is yeah is does it make sense
to really think of a completely isolated
initial state of D Matrix really um and
if so how how do you get what's the
context that drives that initial
probability because it sounds like
without any context every state is
equally as likely as each
other so um if I understand your
question correctly like you know you
take a the the D Matrix at the beginning
of a of the discreet time pomdp active
inference problem right you're saying
that say that there's only four possible
states in the environment that it could
be and here is my my belief about the
probability or expectation about which
one is most likely right so you're
asking like but you know any agent that
exists I mean you know you can say
like I don't know if it's birth or when
you're a clump of cells at a certain
point whatever you know what is the
starting point like is that was that
agent really starting with just like
okay here's my initial State now I'm in
my simulation begins right that's how we
do it we model right but is that what
you're kind of asking like what about
there it's unbounded right because
there's infinite number of states
effectively yes I I guess the issue that
I think people have and maybe I had
until I sort of saw this written out is
that when you have like a tensor or a
matrix there's not one thing in that
right and I think that's so you have the
big letter this is something that
actually recently I've sort of properly
got my head around you have the big
letter which is the tensor yeah and then
you have the small letter um which is
the is that the beliefs encoded in the
tensor am I getting this right those are
the parameters of the tensor right yeah
which are the same in this case it's the
same thing because we represent the
tensors themselves are the parameters
that's how we do them but the question
is where do those values come from right
so lowercase D would be you have these
states with those probabilities how do
you learn what those probabilities are
in the first place assuming there's only
four for example right we're already
restricting it that's you can call that
a prior right we only the agent beli
there's only four states in the
environment um but then the question is
how do we learn what those particular
probabilities are that's what the lower
case D comes I'm just sort of curious
yeah so yeah I guess I'm just curious
about what what does that even look like
when I say I have four potential states
that might be encoded in my deter so I
get you know when I feel like when uh
when someone like me who's interested in
computational phenomenology but learning
it and is coming from the philosophy and
the phenomenology one understands what a
d tensor is and a b tensor and an a
tensor because like it's like oh it's
that but then the fact what what does it
mean for something to be built into that
tensor such that let's say you have
multiple States in a d tensor with
multiple different distributions like
what what does that actually look like
is that just is that purely a
mathematical modeling thing or is there
a way that we can intuitively think
about
that so uh if I think am I'm
understanding your question correctly I
think
um the issue you're describing here is
something that I think is what I've
wondered like this is a model ultimately
right like it's a model of a very simple
scenarios because that's originally
where active inference was came from was
can we model simple human animal
behaviors in a very restricted
environment so if you restrict your
environment to a tze where you know m is
at one end of a teamas and it can only
move in four places it can only exist in
those
States yeah okay then you can you know
in that it's an abstraction of a real
physical real world scenario um in
reality um you know these are it's
actually all continuous when you get
down to it right like I think the
discret state space formulation is kind
of an abstraction to think about
highlevel categories uh which themselves
are encoded neuronal
Dynamics the question is like you know
let's say you really made a real agent
that you were going to put into the
world say it's a robot um and it's going
interact with anything right well what
does its D Matrix look like is it an
infinite Vector
right um I think that's kind of the open
problem is like how do you actually do
that for a real agent I mean there are
states of the world that I don't even
know exist right so yeah if I have a d
Vector right like it's not there yet and
so what I think would probably need to
happen is you have a d Vector that has
the ability to grow is one way you could
treat the problem so if it encounters a
new kind of state that's that's just
something it has never explored before
you add in a new slot to the D vector
and have to recalculate recalibrate all
your probabilities relative to that um
something like that I think is that's
getting up to what you're asking yeah
yeah I mean my my intuition here is that
it's really important to always also C
curtail the state space or the belief
space in these tensors so I've just
written this paper just weing the
preprint it's a more sort of cognitive
sciency philosophy paper it's basically
about how underactive inference for my
eyes something like
attention is always constrained by
preferences so it doesn't really make
sense to talk about like I I'm trying to
collapse this classic endogenous
exogenous distinction that exists in the
intentional literature because under Act
of inference I'm saying well think about
what you're paying attention to it's
always that which is most Salient to you
and that's always governed by your prior
preferences but then what I kind what
kind of came to mind is well it's not
every single prior preference is
exerting pressure on your attentional
schema at any given time right I am not
simultaneously paying attention to how
hungry I am how tired I am and so on
there's got to be some context driving
mechanism that means that when I get
hungry I start paying you know I start
paying attention to food when I
recognize my child is in the Middle Road
I start paying more attention to the
cars and the future you know the
prospect of them getting hit and and so
on and so forth
which again implies some kind of
paradoxical circular causality because I
need to be paying attention to that in
the first place to drive my con
constrain State space such that those
preferences continue to drive the
attentional specification and that's
kind of similar to what I'm talking
about with this D Matrix right I can't
entertain every single possible probable
State it's just computationally
intractable but I also but for me to
know which states are going to at least
be feasible I need toay I need to be
observing the world right like I don't
know if I'm in Iceland or if I'm in the
Sahara and so on so this is kind of what
I meant by is there such a thing as the
detener because an
unbounded detent so-called prior to
Observation to my more philosophically
leaning mind sounds like it just could
consider absolutely everything which it
clearly doesn't so it makes me think oh
is the dent are just the kind of be
tents are
in you know in
Disguise um sorry I rambled I rambled no
but I mean to answer your question that
is exactly what the D tensor is because
if you slice a benser with an action you
get a vector out of it that right
because that's the whole idea is that
it's like assuming whatever ended up
happening this is now the state that
you're in you can kind of think of it
that way because um whenever you you
slice the B Matrix you you get back that
slice only and whatever slice happened
to be your starting slice it's kind of a
way there's no action that preceded it
because it's your starting at the
beginning of the simulation but that's
why it's a vector is because it's
actually that's what ends up happening
when you take an action is you do slice
the benser into a vector and say like
okay I'm transitioning and now that
becomes my my prior um that we use for
the next round of inference um so uh
that's that's just just wanted to
comment on that uh your question that
you're asking is a really deep question
that I don't I don't know if there's a
good answer to that yet like what does
it look like when you you know is there
are deters floating around and being
computed in the brain somewhere like
what do they look like is that what
you're kind of asking like they're just
this unbounded entities like I thinking
is that there's got to be some topown
constraints which is
context related because yeah you know we
can't just at a very basic level we
can't
consider let's say in terms of action we
can't consider every possible action
right because there's infinite things in
principle every infinite gradations of
things at least that I can do in any
given context and so this is I I'm not
the first to think this right there's um
Carl's sophisticated active inference
paper with Lance and others where they
talk about you probably do need a higher
higher order action policy which
constrains the possible actions that you
might take in given context and and when
I was thinking about this attention
paper I was thinking well so people talk
about for example hunger has really high
Precision I'm like okay and then people
say well Precision is attention and I'm
like well no because I'm not always
thinking about how hungry I am and so
what I do is I try to disambiguate
precision and precision waiting and
attention and all of these different
categories but what I'm saying here is
there has to be a there has to be a sing
that says say Well when I'm hungry
because I need I need to eat when I'm
starving over everything right I need to
stop buying my essay I need to stop
speaking to people I need to eat there
needs to be some prioritization
mechanism that says when your glucose
drops below this point everything gets
focused on
food now on one hand yeah that makes
sense because presumably my set point my
homeostatic set point is very deep in my
generative model so it trickles down all
of the predictions at the same time it's
still notle unless you have that higher
order action policy why you would even
prioritize hunger over playing a video
game so I I think I wonder whether Act
of influence needs to go in this
direction and say
well what is constraining these spaces
in the first place all well and good
having them but that's really my
fundamental question here is do we need
to invoke something like a high order
action policy just to constrain the
possible beliefs that we can have in a
generative model
I guess the answer is yes yes yeah
definitely and I think um this area is
something that I've actually been I've
been reading um just just last couple
days for one of the chapters I'm writing
um and uh I I still don't have a great
grasp with the literature but here's
just kind of a sketch of my
understanding uh to answer or just at
least address my speculation on what
you're asking um so there
is you know the idea of attention in the
in the act of
inference uh
formulation is attention is also active
right like you you can choose what
you're attending to at one time so
attention is usually considered like the
the newsworthiness of something so how
Salient or how in interesting or
informative is something at one point in
time or another uh which in the active
inference model like you say there's a
Precision waiting on the signals the
prediction error signals um for either
Sensations or state Transitions and
things like that um
so but it's context dependent there's a
paper recently about social cues in
context so just as an example of a word
I'll i s that paper later I think you
might find it interesting but it's like
even the example of a word right a word
in isolation has no particular it may
have many many different meanings so now
there's uncertainty you have a signal
someone says a word right that's not
enough because there's uncertainty in
the actual content of that signal it
could mean so many different things but
right the context might now that scope
and tell you what it actually has what
the actual meaning of that word is in
the sentence that you're using it right
so the context would be the sentence in
this case um I was very inspired yeah I
was very inspired by b b mit's work um
he's got all of 2016 2017 especially
2019 paper with Carl on selective
attention which I think you if you
haven't read it you would really really
like okay shows that like context so for
example if I'm doing a Yus task which is
a classic attentional Paradigm where uh
someone says you know you show a picture
of a family let's say and they say well
how much do you think this family is
worth and then all they do is look at
the furniture and their clothes and then
they say uh I don't know uh do these F I
don't know actually what the second
condition is it's like do you think this
family get along and all they look at
the eyes and they look at how they're
looking at one another what that shows
is in like what's Salient I actually
prefer the term relevant but that's for
technical attentional reasons but
doesn't really matter um what's relevant
is always relative to context right it
complete it's so it's always contingent
on the goals of the agent at the
time but then you get I think the issue
that I kind of skirted and made need to
think about is you you you potentially
end up in an infinite regress because
you say okay I have a higher order
context or a higher order action policy
that is saying for example when I'm
hungry prioritize hunger over the fact I
want to finish this video game level
okay M but then what then you but then
someone might come along and say well
why is that higher order action policy
relevant right maybe that's just a
hidden state for another higher order
action
policy and so you may end up with this
infinite regress of saying well where
does the relevance kind of stop and
maybe you just get something like
embedded priors genetically embedded
prior that get you out of that hole um
because I can't really see any other way
out of it but all of that to say that I
think I think context is really
important in terms of guiding the
Precision waiting of beliefs I don't
like the term I don't like the although
okay I don't like the alision of
precision and precision waiting because
Precision for me is a very mathematical
term and precision waiting is a much
richer term MH but you're absolutely
right attention is not
only pulled towards something it's also
d uh you know often times seemingly
purposefully directed like the point I
was trying to make in this paper is that
it's fundamentally gold directed even at
the very lowest level right like even in
terms of like color
discrimination you could you know you
can describe it as if your visual
neurons have these prior preferences and
so on anyway so
actually it would be worth saying about
this like you know I'm trying to I'm
trying to work through your question
like probabilistically so we don't get
into the like you know philosophically
it's very hard to talk about these
things cuz like but I'm trying to look
at like actual model right um so let's
just say that you know
hunger is a random variable right like
your state of being hungry which is
dependent on uh blood glucose
levels right so your body is actively
sensing your your your you know the um
your your bloodstream hormones are sent
out you know those levels come back a
sensory information and that's a sensory
signal you get from your body that your
brain will then say okay blood glucose
is a thing I'm measuring here it's gone
down to a certain range and that there's
a prior literally in an invasion sense
there's a prior on um blood glucose that
has you know distribution of acceptable
range and so now that the state is
changed conditioning on that
distribution makes hunger now more
likely or more expected in the model
yeah because blood glucose has now
fallen
um so I'm I'm thinking of it through
conditioning right these effects are all
conditioned variables where the state of
hunger becomes more likely because it's
conditioned on some other thing that's
being measured so it's kind
of I don't know if it's like an
operating system right where there's
like tasks and you know you're sending
something up to the top is like process
this first you know but it feels like
this queing like kind of happens through
the distributions is kind of what I'm
saying but that's the question right is
now that the body recognizes it's
hungry why does it say okay I'm not I'm
going to stop petting my dog or playing
on my phone and I'm going to go get food
and let's say it's
starving and that's all it can think
about it's all it's paying attention to
what is governing that okay well you go
there's a higher order policy because it
has to be which says okay given this
hidden State now now so the the the
hidden state of hunger has become an
observation for a higher order action
policy which says given this this
observation go find food my point with
the infinite regress
is is there an action policy I've got to
try and make sure I guess right I didn't
write this in the paper so this is
actually very influenced by John V's
work on relevance realization so if
anyone's curious about this argument he
puts it in his it's in his relevance
realization paper so I'm butchering it
sorry John John might be watching sorry
John um but the idea would be why what
you know is there an action policy
guiding that action
policy like where does the limit where
does it stop because you might say well
why would I when I'm hungry go and find
food and that's because you have a
higher order action policy which says
that given your observation that there
is this action
policy and so on and so forth so I think
there's an important question here which
might be remaining in the active in
literatures which is where does the cap
of context stop like is there a point at
which it just
stops and where does that come from and
again I think the answer probably has to
be that it's
evolutionary um but that's boring B well
it is I don't know if you would call it
a cop out but that's kind of what you
end up having to do at some point right
like when you have this regress if you
were saying like the boring answer is
well you know we have these DNA is
compressed source code of all these
other things that you know we've
experienced and it overrides other
things right I guess um yeah I don't
know if I have a good answer to your
question other than just saying like if
you're talking in a purely beian sense
like if you just had uh Bas theorem um
and you increase the because the
Precision right the Precision is also
learned from the data that's also part
of right like you learn how much to
modulate that Precision um you know if
you have just even a three-way Network
where you have your data you have hunger
and you have play games um and those two
things are being integrated together to
have this distribution over like what do
I do um like what's the next you know do
I eat or do I play games what what's
you're inferring from the data well if
you're learning from the data the
Precision is much higher on the
distribution for Hunger then its waiting
is much more higher Invasion inference
than the gaming playing games and so
your posterior will be weighted much
more highly toward the state would be
more likely is getting food yeah so I
don't know if you even need to evoke
that infinite regress other than
I'm not sure I'm thinking about this
through this I'm not maybe we're not
understanding I'm not understanding your
question but no no I think you are I
think you when I've spoken to John about
it I have said I think you get out of
the infinite regress through
Evolution um or you get out of it
through well in yeah you could say
learning right whether it's um kind of
this supervised learning over e EPO or
whether it's in real time I think the
problem with in real time learning is
like why if it's it's not evolutionary
and it is in real time why would the
system prioritize those you know the
Precision waiting of those signals over
others and then maybe you end up in the
infinite regress I do think at a certain
point you have to bottom out somewhere
you're right because I mean why is it in
the first place that food is you know
why is distribution constru where did
that distribution come from in the first
place like why is it constructed that
way exactly yeah that's exactly that's
the point right like yeah and I'm just
really curious about what these what's
the drive because I I I invoke this kind
of notion again of like a circular
causality between attention and
preferences whereby for me to
prioritize a preference in my Precision
waiting right for me to go okay uh the
prior for Hunger is now more you know
heavy in Precision waiting than the
prior to get you know play video games
well I need to pay atten as I said
before I need to pay attention to the
observations that I'm making so as to
drive that which in turn drives my
attention towards that and you get these
kinds of positive feedback loops um
which I think actually also end up
explaining something like addiction and
maybe in the count you know I know John
would argue that the opposite of that
would be something like AAP agapic love
where you're one with the universe but
anyway we don't have to go there um if I
can I will find what John says about
relevance realization because I
think it's a um it's his it's his kind
of it's his response in some ways to the
frame problem so the frame problem being
well how do you know like if you're an
artificial intelligent being how do you
know which information to zero in on um
okay because you have a pol well how do
you end up with a policy to zero in on
that information where you have a higher
order policy what how do you have that
and so so that's the infinite regress is
the infinite regress of the frame
problem but I guess when you bottom up
we're just going around Circle that but
when you bottom out with Evolution you
seemingly resolve that problem I think
so and that's just as an example and I
think I I'm not sure this is true but I
believe it's true that I read somewhere
that um like infants will um you know
I'm talking like very small infants few
months old they will um I don't know
what the exact age is so I can't give a
great um answer on this but they will
prefer they will you know be selective
about the kind of liquids they will
ingest so like sweet things is one
example but like bitter or you know
salty there could be those could be
poisons so you and there are many other
things too like suckling Behavior other
instinctual things that infants within
first few weeks have the awareness of or
ability to to do these sorts of very
very basic behaviors where does that
come from right because if you're you
know there aren't any where are those
priors coming from I think you have to
bottom out on some level of evolution in
some way eventually um but along that
way in the development right I think
there's so many other things that happen
in there and a lot of it is also
cultural things you know you were taught
um even in the early um reinforcement
learning or active inference paper 2009
with Carl's paper with a few other
authors on there they actually use
supervised learning to teach the model
it's like priors first to solve the
mountain car problem right so like I
think and they argue like well you know
people you know you learn from other
people like your caretaker caregivers uh
people around you teach you some things
so I think that's the other option it's
either evolutionary or it's learned very
very early on as something that you
learn during development that becomes
encoded as this as this highly precise
thing um but that's just speculation I'm
not quite sure no it's fascinating I
mean it goes back it's really it's
really amazing I mean I think active
inference in giving us these kinds of
phenotypic priors answer so many
questions that were long-standing in
cognitive science I mean like this
argument of kind of foundational
Concepts goes to back to Someone Like
Jerry Fodor and Fodor saying well we
kind of need these innate Concepts you
know um because how would I ever be able
you know it's almost platonic it's it is
a PL argument you know how could I ever
bracket something into the concept of
red rather than blue without already
having the concept of red and Plato
argues that you have the form of red and
Carl will say well no you have a sort
Proto foundational prior that allows you
to do this assortment so thank God for
Mr friston um let's um let's finish up
just by talking about verses so people
are probably aware of what versus is but
if they're not um maybe you can give
just like sort of a brief overview of
what versus is what the ambition is um
and also what you do there because I'm
sure people are very
curious sure um so I've only started
versus in um December so uh versus in
any ways is still very new to me so this
is um just to give an overview uh for
verses um versus in um about maybe I
think it's almost two years now um Carl
and um many of the researchers that were
working with him joined the uh versus
R&D group so uh versus AI company
they're working on um active inference
models um and U applying them um and
scaling them and learning how to use
active inference models in more
realistic
uh settings so kind of the scope of when
we talk about versus um we look at how
we have you know natural Intelligence on
one hand and artificial intelligence so
that's kind of the way we're reframing
it we're thinking about how do
biological systems intelligently do
things um bi biology biologically
inspired intelligence and how can we
engineer those things using active
inference so in one sense like the R&D
group is continuing the work that Carl
was doing with many of his colleagues
but now we're trying to apply them in uh
specific settings so I can't talk a lot
about the actual research itself of
course I'm not you know but so I'm
giving more of a very very high level
explanation um but the major uh
contribution is you know we have
definitely Open Source papers that have
you know been published a couple like on
Federated Act of inference as one
example the inductive inference paper uh
there's a couple others on structure
learning that came out recently um so
there is some insight into some of uh
the the work that's being done at versus
there through those papers um but more
generally versus is focused on the in
vision of the spatial web um which uh
there's a book uh the CEO of of versus
Gabriel as well as Dan Mapes they wrot
co-wrote a book together the spatial web
which is uh looking at the future of
what the internet could be so looking at
the isolated technologies that are that
make up web 3 um when you look at things
like um uh blockchain and arvr
Technologies internet of things and
smart cities and things like that uh
digital twins they all have their own
little research area they're all kind of
being different companies in isolation
are studying these things so the idea is
to put them together into one umbrella
um where we have the new version of the
internet where you don't really have web
pages anymore but you have people places
and things so there's so much to unpack
in that umbrella um that we could talk
about that the book goes into and I'm
still myself learning and getting my
hands on all the uh details of that but
it is um the new web standards that
would come out of this are we registered
with itle e so you can attend uh look at
the documents and things like that that
are part of the development of the
spatial web and active inference is
playing the core AI component of what
the spatial web will entail so it's kind
of functioning as you know the yeah the
broader scale of it how can we take it
out of the neurosciences and scale it up
into something that can be used these
kinds of
Technologies really cool really really
cool and a lovely explanation
um I was curious just when I heard you
you know you one does hear the versus
people talk about mimicking or or
replicating biotic intelligence in
artificial uh
entities how much do you guys again this
is a very high level question because I
don't want Maxwell to shout at me but
how much do you guys run into like the
as if that we've already discussed
namely maybe in terms of like the ground
truth of active inference is that things
look as if they are conducting
variational basing inference over their
external States but how they're doing
that whether they're actually doing that
right these are still kind of live
debates I'm wondering whether when you
translate that over to an artificial
intelligence agent it leaves you a
little bit well up in the air about okay
exactly we we can say okay they have to
be abiding by by the free energy
principle they have to look as if
they're minimizing variational free
energy but is there a problem where you
go well how on Earth are we how what's
the process Theory how are they actually
going to be looking as if they're doing
that so what's the kind of yeah I'm
curious about how you how you skirt that
problem so I think these are I mean
these are the kinds of things that will
probably look
different these discussions look
different to different people depending
on your your philosophical
presuppositions so different researchers
at versus and outside of versus all have
different takes on this um so my
personal take is that the as if problem
you know is not as important I don't
think in an engineering setting because
ultimately it's sort of the scientific
process about okay I'm making this model
that I want to do something in this
world and I and it needs to predict in a
certain way it needs to do these certain
things is it doing that it's not then
what do we what is it missing that we
need to add to make it make it and if
end of the day I mean I don't think it
really matters if something is totally
mimicking human like intelligence in a
way that for all intense and purposes
maybe like kind of the the Grand Touring
test of uh you know in general of any
kind of skill or thing that it can
reason about if it's doing that
effectively then I feel like the as if
question doesn't really matter for this
kind of a circumstance and yeah you
start think about Consciousness and the
effects of conscious Ai and whether
something like embodied cognition active
inference yields Consciousness again
these are deep philosophical
questions yeah I agree yeah I just
wonder whether when when I think about
active inference and I the more time I
spend with it the less Concrete in a
Socratic way about what I can say
exactly it's claiming right um because
sure you have the mathematical
derivations but you know going all the
way back to just basic analytical
philosophy all the maths just turns in
on itself right it's an analy it's an
analytic truth it's kind of tautological
it doesn't necessarily tell you anything
about the world apart from the fact that
things have to look as if they're
abiding by this principle like things
look like they're abiding by hamiltonian
law of least principle of least action
so I'm just wondering whether in an
engineering sense right so in a very
pragmatic sense what and again not
revealing any secrets because ndas and
Maxwell scary um joking
um how can you even like how do you get
from okay you have like the vfe equation
or the EF
equation and then you have these kinds
of offshoots like predictive coding or
Pond DP schema or variational message
passing and so
on how do you kind of choose in a way um
which one's the best option and also
then we have to build in this issue of
okay we got discret State space we've
got continuous State space in reality
everything's hybrid so I'm just
wondering whether how you can get from
like a super fundamental mathematical
Axiom like the variational free energy
formula to something that can actually
be programmed and is applicable and I
guess this comes to a question of how
does someone decide what kind of
simulation to run in the first
place yeah I mean this is a this is a
big problem that will come from scaling
any technology but active inference you
know if you even just look at the
robotics papers that already it kind of
come out the last 5 years or so there's
been a lot more exploration in that area
um a lot of them have to make practical
considerations and tricks to make it
work in the robotic setting so whether
that's you know further approximations
of certain signals that are just taken
for granted and the equations you know
it's like well there's latency issues
there's all these other things that you
know you have to deal with and these
robotics papers often start with the
core of active inference and then throw
a bunch of other things on top of it so
the most common trick is the like
amortised inference um which would be
like you
know you you know it's taken for granted
if you have a small tiny little you know
toy simulation oh my generative model is
this linear equation or this quadratic
or whatever it is um how do you actually
you know you already have learned those
variables okay well how do you do that
in a setting where it's this huge
multi-dimensional thing well you can use
deep learning use some Universal
function approximator that learns the
parameters of all these
distributions so the you know the broad
answer to your question is is like you
come up you hit a wall with a lot of
these sorts of things when you look at
like the robotics literature um and
you're trying to engineer these sorts of
systems where you have to start
including tricks that were not
necessarily in the original formulations
and you think okay well you know I have
to prune my my policy tree there's so
many different options here how do I
figure out what's the best action to
take because I have to do an engineering
setting um and so there's a paper
recently on reactive um uh decision
trees uh reactive uh behavioral trees in
uh in robotics that came out a couple
years ago another perspective looking at
branching time active inference for
example so these are all like little
modifications on the original
methodology the core is still the same
but you can add these extra layers on
there so you make better predictions and
you can actually function and build
systems in the real world and I think
it's it's sort of like a guess in check
like you you build a simulation or you
build a robot and you realize okay
there's a major limitation here what do
we need to add onto the system
mathematically for it to actually deal
with that problem and I see this as an
iterative process like you don't know
starting out like you start out with
just the basic model and then you
realize wait that doesn't work very well
and then you keep adding components on
there till you get a more holistic model
that can make better predictions you
guys are very pragmatic it's very good
it's very good it's very yeah I like it
all engineering is right yeah yeah yeah
yeah no it's um yes uh yeah yeah well
let me know let me know how you guys get
about with this pruning via context
problem cuz I think that's a problem and
I'm curious about how that's getting
done probably again with these uh
phenotypic priors um I did actually get
up this vvi thing so I'll mention it
because you might be interested because
it actually comes from artificial
intelligence so this is actually from a
really nice paper which was in
phenomenology and the cognitive Sciences
by Brett Anderson Mark Miller and John
vvi called predictive processing
relevance realization exploring
convergent solutions to the frame
problem and therein they say and I will
get it
up um in the middle of the 20th century
artificial intelligence researchers
discovered what dennet 1987 called a new
deep epistemological problem that came
to be known as the frame problem in its
original form the problem consisted of
how to program an artificially
intelligent agent to intelligently take
into account the side effects of its
actions for example if a robot needs to
retrieve a battery but the battery is on
a wagon that also has a on it the robot
must be able to realize that retrieving
the battery will bring the bomb along
with it thus resulting in its own
destruction this may seem like a
relatively simple issue but it turned
out to be incredibly complicated the
problem is that there are a near
infinite number of potential side
effects to any particular action how can
we program the robot to take into
account the relevant side effects while
intelligently ignoring the irrelevant
one we cannot program the robot to
systematically assess all of the
possibilities because there are far too
many um
and so I guess that idea is uh okay you
you give it a prior which says you know
don't pick up wagons with bombs on them
but then there's a potential side effect
that lams if there's a child underneath
it and you want to pick up the wagon
with the bomb on it and you want to
resolve the child and what you end up
here right you're overfitting on that
scenario right yeah you get massive
overfitting yeah and so what I think
active influence brings him really
nicely to this again this comes out in
my paper I guess is the notion of a
hierarchy and I guess that feeds in
right like if there's a child and you
know if there's a child at risk you do
it and I guess the question of the frame
problem is well what's at the very top
of your hierarchy of values um and maybe
those are are evolutionary priers that's
a really good question I don't you know
of course I don't think anyone knows the
answer to that question but I will point
out when I'm thinking about this what
you you know you brought that up that
you know um you know children
to me children are like that robot like
really like you know toddlers they don't
know the context differences between
things right like but you're taught it
over time if you put them in the world
yeah they're probably going to take that
bomb and they won't know the difference
but we tell them by saying no don't do
that don't do that they learn over time
uh to make those those contexts and I I
don't know exactly like maybe some of it
eventually bottoms out at Evolution but
I think that's what the learning stage
is for you know young children they have
to go through this sort of you know
trial and error where they're doing all
kinds of things that could kill them and
they don't know until a parent tells
them and explains you know like this is
dangerous this is why you know um and
there's still in that in that question
is like how do you then you know how are
all those things ranked where like you
said like what if there's a child like
it doesn't completely solve the problem
but I'm just pointing out that like
perhaps a robot needs to go through like
extensive training um where you know
like if there was a way to encode those
priors maybe we could build them in but
it's probably so complex that the only
way is to make like an infant robot and
have it go up through stages of
development where we start teaching it
things and we you know instruct it and
it starts to build in those those pieces
in there that's just speculation no no
no I think that's ABS I think that's
absolutely right um again the
philosopher in me is saying well why why
and this is the infinite frame problem
why would the child listen to the parent
and try and survive in the first place
and then maybe you do get grounded out
an evolution um there's definitely yeah
the instinct to you know your caregivers
are the you know why is there an
instinct to cry and why you know there
all those sorts of things like their
animals that don't cry out in pain um
are often ones that are not they're ones
that don't have a mother like there's no
there's no one going to help you right
like what you you know crying out in
pain is a social reaction because you
know that others will take care of you
so like yeah is going to be eventually
it's going to be built into social
Customs which again then bottom out into
evolution is my guess right like
eventually all of this is some kind of
foundationalism and active inference
gives us that foundationalism so we it
took me it took me an hour to get there
but we got there so I'm very sorry for
everyone who had and
you I mean these problems are like that
an hour is good to me like I knew this
[ __ ] answer already I already spoke
to John about it for some reason it
didn't come to me but anyway we got
there it's all Evolution uh well it's
not all Evolution it's a hierarchy um
final question yeah uh there's a lot of
hype about deep learning and large
language models and neural networks and
we haven't even touched upon this
podcast's most frequently touched upon
topic which is consciousness and this is
going to be a very flippant factious
question and I want it to be answered in
a flippant fa man factious manner uh are
any large language models that exist
right now
conscious my instinct tells me no um but
I will say that large language models
continuously surprise me with the kinds
of things they can do um the you know
there's all this research coming out
right now about like well what appears
to be imersion is really you know not
now that we kind of like kind of look at
it a bit more closely um I think
that it's worth considering um not that
they're conscious but there may be some
level
of I'm trying to think of the right word
here cuz like you know self-awareness
all those things are not quite there but
there's always this argument like oh
well something is mimicking it it's not
actually the same thing as that like a
parot right kind of thing like he
doesn't understand the meaning of the
words where does that boundary get
crossed because there's eventually a
point right where the mimicry is the
same as the actual thing right and I
don't know very deep it's a very deep
philosophical question um which could
only be answered in factious ways
because it's it's hundreds of years of
thinking yeah well SS Chinese rumors
well you just classic you don't yeah the
idea you just don't right like you do
the mimickry and actually well you know
there might be some people who say that
Chinese room is conscious um that's by
yeah you're Guided by intuition if you
don't have a definition of what
conscious is which we don't it's really
hard I think we have only you can do is
you can kind of poke holes in things and
be like well we know we're conscious at
least we think we are and here's what we
do and this thing is not doing that
thing like you know yeah the whole whole
the Chinese room thing is a whole lookup
table right like well yeah yeah yeah
we're not doing a lookup table but
there's some compression going on like
we have a compressed representation of
something is that so is is compression
sufficient and maybe you know how
compressed information or relevant yes
I'm think I'm thinking about these ideas
I'm not going to SP I'm not going to
give any teasers but I'm thinking about
these ideas um okay and final question
is will large language models get get us
there and by get us there I mean um well
actually you can pick you can either
have Consciousness or you can have what
people throw around as you know with the
term General artificial intelligence or
sorry artificial general intelligence
AGI uh God knows what that means but you
may have your own definition so will it
get us either to Consciousness or AGI
take your pick please be
factious personally I find llms really
boring so I mean I just don't find them
very interesting and there's been a lot
of you know hype around them and what
they can do
um you know I'm the kind of person I
don't have a lot of very strong opinions
about these kinds of things because I
feel like we just we just don't know
enough but I can have I have hunches
right I have a hunch that it's not going
to get us far enough um and I don't
think if you throw enough compute power
at an llm eventually you'll have
something out of it and I think the big
reason is because there's so much when
you look at like active inference models
they're not nearly on the scale of you
know they're not llms right but there's
causality there's sense of causality and
structure in the data generation process
that I think you're not completely
recapitulating within llm this is more
of an intuitive feeling I don't have
data to back that up um but when I look
at an llm I don't see it as I see it as
clever memorization with some level of
compression um in there and you if if
it's possible to do you know you take
maybe LMS is too too much to look at but
like a simpler deep learning model can
you take that deep learning model and do
it better with active inference with
less parameters less training time less
data can you do a lot more with a lot
less better
generalization if you can then my hunch
would be that the active inference model
which is obviously where my position
tends toward is compressing or capturing
something in the data much better than a
deep Learning System is now I don't know
what that difference is in what it's
doing but if I had to make a bet I would
make it on that active inference is
doing it better and more compressed in a
way that's probably more scalable and
more likely to bring about so-called AGI
which for me means mimicking human and
animal behavior on reasoning tasks is a
very vague like what we see in each
other as being intelligent Behavior we
recognize it in the systems that we
build and doing it as well as human
performance that's kind of what I would
consider as a vague definition of what a
AGI might be that's good that's a that's
a nice uh it's a weak version of AGI
it's good it's good it's good we're not
going to get anyone too angry with that
one I don't want to commit too hard to
it so no no no well you never know who
listens you never know who listens I
might get you know an email from Jeffrey
Hinton or someone you never know I'm not
I I'm just going to watch um but if
verses need philosophers then well
actually I know there are philosophers
of verses and it sounds like yeah xell
for example but yeah there's others too
yeah and so on well Sanji I think all of
that means that you're absolutely on The
Cutting Edge of well of the future of
intelligence and that's exciting um so I
think well from my side you're you're a
real inspiration and I say that a lot to
people and that's because I mean it
because I'm really really very inspired
and touched by all the people who have
helped me but you have helped me not
only with this textbook but also you
know privately in messages and you've
put up with some terrible questions
probably but they're all questions and
question thank you uh I was waiting for
that um but yeah I think I this
hopefully I mean this podcast I've
really really loved because I think it
shows people that something that can
seem incredibly
complicated well in some sense is but
can be you know it's it's tractable to
use a sort of basian term just given a
lot of hard work determination and and
kind of motivation so you're definitely
a kind of Shining Light although people
may have not you know people may not
know you because you're not sort of one
of these kind of you know you have got
millions of papers out there but
nonetheless it's uh it's a great
pleasure to speak to you and um thank
you for the work you do I always ask
people before they finish just to let
people let the public and the listening
public know where they can be found so
you know if anyone does have any curious
questions about the textbook um and
maybe you want to speak about the
textbook you can give yourself just a
kind of 30- second plug but yeah you
know you know email Twitter whatever
whatever's best yeah email is the best
way to reach me um It's sanjie s n j v.
namjoshi n
mji
gmail.com um you can also find me on the
active inference Institute Discord
Channel if you want to DM me over there
um my website is uh snam ji.
github.io I noticed it hasn't been
picked up by search engines yet so uh I
put it in the video descript but yeah
it's hard to find but I just have a
little bit more about my papers and
research and things um yeah I'm open for
people taking a look at the textbook
basically if you send me an email just
saying you want to look at it I can give
you a link to um the uh Koda page that's
hosted by the active inference Institute
or their chapter drafts and uh just uh
video lectures that I've given still a
work in progress I'm in second um
revision right now and the first there's
two books the first volume is due in on
June 1st um and wow coming up been
pretty pretty slanted and then the next
one is Ban mechanics it'll be much later
but um if you're willing to look through
any drafts and you're very curious about
anything else um you're welcome to send
me an email and I can give you access
and also that's just yeah feel free to
send me an email and I'm happy to talk
awesome sanjie this was awesome really
really fun really informative um thank
you so much great thank you very much I
really appreciate it